A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Human Development and Reproductive Health (HDRH), Office Files of Virginia Davis Floyd FA513
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Human Development and Reproductive Health (HDRH), Office Files of Virginia Davis Floyd
1973-2002, bulk 1994-2002
1994-2002
Rockefeller Archive Center
Floyd, Virginia Davis
Ford Foundation
FA513
5.24 Cubic Feet 4 standard record storage boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
HDRH files of Virginia Davis Floyd.
Arrangement
Arranged in 3 series:
1. Publications and Reports.
2. Meetings.
3. Subject Files.
Biographical / Historical
Virginia Davis Floyd is a physician whose career has included positions in public health, philanthropy, and higher education. From 1997 to 2002, she was Director of the Ford Foundation's Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Human Development and Reproductive Health (HDRH) unit.
Prior to joining the Ford Foundation, Floyd had a series of public and family health positions. In 1979, she was a medical officer for the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and was based in Cameroon. She then joined the National Health Services Corps in Palmetto, Georgia before going to Morehouse College to establish a family medicine residency program. From 1984 to 1997, she served as director of family health at the Georgia Department of Human Resources.
After leaving the Ford Foundation, Floyd became a visiting scholar at Spelman College in 2003. She joined the faculty of Morehouse College in 2006.
Floyd completed her undergraduate education at Spelman College and spent her final year of college studying at Sophia University in Tokyo, Japan. She earned her Doctor of Medicine from Howard University College of Medicine in 1976 and did a residency program at Emory University Hospital. In 1987, she earned a Master's Degree in public health from Emory.
- Publications and Reports, 1973-2001; I
  - Background Papers, 1973 June (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation Publications and Working Papers, 1986-1992 (Box 1)
  - The Changing Context for Movements to Improve Women's Lives, 1986 September 29 (Box 1)
  - The AIDS Challenge -- A Ford Foundation Response, 1987 December (Box 1)
  - Reproductive Health Papers, 1990-1994 (Box 1)
  - Reproductive Health -- A Strategy for the 1990s, 1991 June (Box 1)
  - Reproductive Health in Indonesia -- A Program Paper, 1991 September 20 (Box 1)
  - Violence Against Women -- Addressing a Global Problem, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Program Strategies in Reproductive Health and Population -- Bangladesh, 1992 January (Box 1)
  - Reproductive Health/Reproductive Rights -- Legal, Policy and Ethical Issues, 1992 January (Box 1)
  - Project on Ethics and Reproductive Health -- Visit to the Philippines, 1992 September 28 (Box 1)
  - Trip Report -- Mexico, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Report on Visit to China, 1993 February (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation Reproductive Health and Population Program Meeting Notes, 1993 April 27-30 (Box 1)
  - Ruth Macklin -- Trip Reports (Peru, Colombia, Nigeria), 1994 (Box 1)
  - The World's Rural Poor and How to Assist Them, 1994 September (Box 1)
  - Strengthening Fragile Families -- A Proposed Strategy for the Ford Foundation, 1994 November (Box 1)
  - The Ford Foundation's Neighborhood and Family Initiative -- Interim Report, 1995 September (Box 1)
  - Girls Education and Sexuality -- A Working Paper, 1996 February 14 (Box 1)
  - The Ford Foundation's Reproductive Health and Population Program -- A Five Year Review (Box 1)
  - The Ford Foundation in Bangladesh, circa 1997 (Box 1)
  - Strengthening Fragile Families Initiative Report 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Strengthening Fragile Families Initiative Media and Publications, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Reproductive Health Affinity Group -- Reports/Materials, 1998-2001 (Box 1)
  - Reproductive Health Review Meeting, 1998 May (Box 1)
  - Human Development and Reproductive Health Program Review, 1998 September 15 (Box 1)
  - The Asset Building Framework -- Perspectives and Tools for a Global Program, 1998 November 11 (Box 1)
  - Strengthening Fragile Families Initiative -- Information and Reports, 1999-2001 (Box 1)
  - Survey of Regional Initiatives in Asia in the Field of Human Rights, 1999 August (Box 1)
  - Beyond Borders, 1999 October 9-14 (Box 1)
  - Reproductive Health 2000 (Box 1)
  - Strengthening Fragile Families Initiative Close-out Report, 2000 June 13 (Box 1)
  - Strengthening Fragile Families Initiative -- Final Report on Work of 14 Grantees, 2000 September 30 (Box 1)
  - Working with the Asset Building Framework, 2001 February 5 (Box 1)
  - Background Paper on Reproductive Health -- Kenya, undated (Box 1)
  - Strengthening Fragile Families Initiative, undated (Box 1)
  - The Ford Foundation in the Philippines, undated (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation China Office Publications, undated (Box 1)
- Meetings, 1995-2001; II
  - Reproductive Health and Population Worldwide Meeting, 1995 May 14-19 (Box 2)
  - Human Development and Reproductive Health Initial Staff Meeting, 1996 October 17 (Box 2)
  - Human Development and Reproductive Health Meeting with Grantees on 5-year Review, 1997 March 27-April 15 (Box 2)
  - Sistersong Conference [PHOTOS], 1998 September (Box 2)
  - Human Development Program Review -- Draft, 1998 September 15 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Affinity Group Meeting, 1998 November 7-10 (Box 2)
  - ASSETS Directors/VP Meeting, 1999 September 21 (Box 2)
  - Strengthening Fragile Families Initiative Quarterly Grantee Meeting, 2000 March 1 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health Affinity Group Meeting, 2000 June 7 (Box 2)
  - Beijing +5 Photographs and Background Information [PHOTOS], 2000 June 8 (Box 2)
  - Beijing +5 Reports, 2000 June 8 (Box 2)
  - Reproductive Health -- Field -- HIV/AIDS Roundtable -- Vietnam, 2001 (Box 2)
  - PCI Screening -- Ford Foundation Level B Auditorium, 2001 April 5 (Box 2)
  - International AIDS Issues, 2001 May 4 (Box 2)
  - International Funders Meeting, 2001 May 14-15 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Meeting, 2001 May 23-25 (Box 2)
  - Leadership Forum on HIV Prevention, 2001 June 22 (Box 2)
  - Healthy Wealthy Wise Meeting, 2001 October 28-30 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation Board of Trustees Meeting, 2002 May 21-22 (Box 2)
- Subject Files, 1984-2002; III
  - Arts Subgroup, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
  - Big Bet -- Sexuality -- Review, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Big Bet -- Sexuality, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Big Bet -- Sexuality -- Roundtables -- Staff Meetings, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Capacity Building Assistance Teams, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Community and Resource Development Administration, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Culture and Religion Sub-Group, 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - Hempel, Margaret -- Handover Notebook, 1987-1999 (Box 3)
  - Hempel, Margaret -- Handover Notes, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Hempel/Muecke -- Old Reports, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  - Human Development and Reproductive Health -- Program Officer Memoranda, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Human Development and Reproductive Health, 1998-2000 (Box 3)
  - Human Development and Reproductive Health -- Material from Muecke, Margorie, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Human Development and Reproductive Health -- Children, Youth and Families, 1999-2001 (Box 3)
  - Human Development and Reproductive Health -- Sexual Health and Well-Being, 2002 (Box 3)
  - International AIDS Presentation -- Durban, 1999 (Box 3)
  - (IWHC) International Women's Health Coalition -- Sexuality and Reproductive Health, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Mature CDC Initiative, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Media Subgroup, 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Exit Memorandum, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment A -- Program Officer Memorandum, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment B -- Community Youth Development Initiative Component I, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment C -- Community Youth Development Initiative Component II, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment D -- Youth Leadership for Development Initiative, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment E -- Youth Development Communique, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment F -- Exchange Reports -- Kenya, Nigeria, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment G -- Most Recent DOL/OOP Update, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment H -- CARTA's Workplan and Service Agreement, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment I -- History of Foundations Work in Youth Development, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment J -- Grantee List, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Mohomad, Inca A. -- Exit Memo -- Attachment K -- Miscellaneous Materials on Youth Development, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Population Communication Africa, 2001 February (Box 4)
  - (RHAG) Reproductive Health Affinity Group, 1998-2000 (Box 4)
  - (RHAG) Reproductive Health Affinity Group -- General, 1999-2001 (Box 4)
  - Sistersong -- Consultants, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
  - Teenage Pregnancy, 1984-1998 (Box 4)